Guide to the National Council of Jewish Women, Pittsburgh Section Records, 1894-2011 AIS.1964.40
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Administration, 1921-1977; V.
  - Finance Committee, 1.
    - Policy and Personnel
      - Minutes, 1935-1946 (Box 14, Folder 3-4)
      - Correspondence, Departmental Committee, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Minutes, Special Committee on the Office of President, 1949 (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - Reports, Administration and Finance, 1949-1967 (Box 14, Folder 7-9)
      - Office Service Committee, 1946-1961 (Box 14, Folder 10-12)
      - Personnel Committee, 1949-1972 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Program, Publicity, and Public Relations, 2.
    - Reports and correspondence, 1927-1977 (Box 14, Folder 14-20)
    - Program material, invitations, and newspaper clippings (Box 14, Folder 21-22)
- Fundraising, 1927-1979; VI.
  Series VI contains materials for the Pittsburgh Sections fundraising activities. One of the Section's first projects was fundraising. Most early fundraising was ad hoc, to cover the expenses of renting a hall for a lecture, for example. An early campaign raised a little over $1,630 to give to the Pittsburgh and Allegheny Free Kindergarten Association for the establishment of a new kindergarten. The school was named "Columbian Kindergarten" in honor of the Columbian Council. In 1897 the increasing expenditure of funds for philanthropy led the Section to inaugurate other fundraising techniques, including special memberships, personal solicitations, and memorials. In 1909 the Section introduced a Ways and Means Committee whose purpose was fundraising. The committee introduced sponsorship of theatrical events, guest lectures, and souvenir programs, which were very successful. The first supper dance and automobile raffles were introduced in 1917 and balls, fashion shows, dinner dances, and carnivals were popular through the 1930s and 1940s. In the late 1950s extravagant musicals were produced featuring members of the Section. During the 1970s the low key Stay-At-Home Balls replaced the Angel Balls of the 1960s.
  However, the Section's most successful, ongoing fundraising has been through their thrift shops. Thrift shops were inaugurated by Mrs. Minnie Kaufmann in 1927. She stated their purpose to be, "to utilize the waste of the Jewish community, to collect, and dispose of rummage." The Service Shop, and later the Council Shop, have been located at various addresses throughout Pittsburgh.
  - Ways and Means, 1.
    - Historic letters about Columbian Kindergarten (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
    - Committee reports and correspondence, 1950-1973 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Remembrance, anniversary, and memorial fund, 1938-1960 (Box 15, Folder 4-5)
    - Report, Benefit Ball, 1934-1935 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Carnivals, 1946-1948 (Box 15, Folder 7-8)
    - Benefit performance "Fun and Funds", 1949 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - "The Magic of Fall Fashion", 1950 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Dinner dance and fashion revue, 1951 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - "Evening in Paris", 1952 (Box 15, Folder 12-14)
    - "Americana Dinner Dance", 1953 (Box 15, Folder 15-17)
    - Sixtieth birthday dinner dance, 1954 (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Dessert luncheon fashion show, 1955 (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - "My Fair Lady", 1956 (Box 15, Folder 20-24)
    - "The Bells Are Ringing", 1957 (Box 16, Folder 1-4)
    - "Three to Make Ready", 1958 (Box 16, Folder 5-8)
    - Talent, Inc. (Sections's "little theatre group") (Box 16, Folder 9-11)
    - "Angel Balls," reports, invitations, and newspaper clippings, 1961-1970 (Box 16, Folder 12-15)
    - "Stay-at-Home Balls", 1968-1979 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Tour programs, 1966-1968 (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Lists of fundraising aides and contributors (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Service/Council Shops, 1927-1973 (Box 16, Folder 19-25)
    - Council Boutique (Anathan House) and "Designer Dress Day", 1970-1973 (Box 16, Folder 26-26a)
- Education, 1894-1974; VII.
  Series VII consists of records regarding the overall goals of the Pittsburgh Section. When the NCJW was organized at the Columbian Exposition in 1893 four resolutions were passed which served as the basis of its constitution. These resolutions emphasized working in religion, education, and philanthropy, studying Judaism, improving Sabbath schools, and opposing religious persecution. Each local section was given considerable leeway in implementing these goals.
  The Pittsburgh Section has worked, sometimes in cooperation with other groups, to encourage Jewish education. Shortly after its founding the Columbian Council organized study circles and the earliest standing committee, the Committee on Religion. The religious education of children, especially the children of immigrants, was the Council's earliest outreach project. In January of 1896 they started a religious school which became the nucleus of the Columbian School and Settlement, later renamed the Irene Kaufmann Settlement. The Settlement separated from the Council in 1900, but the religious school continued under the Council's direction. In 1927 the Sisterhood of Rodef Shalom joined the Pittsburgh Section to form the Southwestern District of Pennsylvania Jewish Religious Schools Committee. This relationship lasted until 1964. For more information on this subject see Mildred W. Kreimer's, "Southwestern District Religious Schools Celebrate Sixtieth Year," Jewish Criterion, September 11, 1953.
  - Religious Education, 1.
    - Historic correspondence on religious education, 1894-190(?) (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
    - Reports, by-laws, correspondence, members, and schools, Southwestern District of Pennsylvania Jewish Religious Schools Committee, 1927-1964 (Box 17, Folder 3-14)
    - Religious study programs, 1920s-1958 (Box 17, Folder 15-16)
    - Contemporary Jewish affairs, 1950-1974 (Box 17, Folder 17-19)
    - Jewish education in Pittsburgh, 1946-1956 (Box 17, Folder 20-22)
  - English as a Second Language (ESL), 2.
    - Course Material, 1980-1982 (Box 17A, Folder 1)
    - 1989 (Box 17A, Folder 2)
    - Volunteer Registration, 1989-1991 (Box 17A, Folder 3)
    - Volunteer Tutor Training, 1991 (Box 17A, Folder 4)
    - Tutor lists (Box 17A, Folder 5)
    - Tutor Packets (Box 17A, Folder 6)
    - Grants, 1990 (Box 17A, Folder 7)
    - Partners in Conversation, 1990-1993 (Box 17A, Folder 8)
    - Public Relations, 1990-1994 (Box 17A, Folder 9)
- Philanthropic Activities, 1901-1975; VIII.
  Series VIII contains materials on the Pittsburgh Sections philanthropic activities. To implement the goal of philanthropy the NCJW Pittsburgh Section involved itself in numerous activities. A Personal Service Committee, formed in 1895 performed traditional acts of charity, including visiting the poor and sick, donating food and clothing, and providing medical care. The Personal Service Committee was disbanded in 1912 with the establishment of the Federation of Jewish Philanthropies.
  Another early interest of Section's was to aid immigrants, which developed from informal relationships based on involvement in settlement work to a full-fledged department with a professional at its head. The Pittsburgh Section was also interested in working with girls, often immigrants, and helping them to find housing, employment, and recreation. In 1946 the NCJW's Service for Foreign Born merged with the National Refugee Service into the United Service for New Americans (USNA). However, the committees for Service to Foreign Born continued functioning at the section level. In 1954 the Hebrew Sheltering and Immigrant Aid Society (HIAS) and the refugee services of the Joint Distribution Committee joined the USNA to form a unified agency, United HIAS Service, Inc. In the Foreign Born subseries there is information on activities relating to the immigration and rescue efforts in Europe, as well as other functions for new citizens.
  This series also contains materials relating to the Section's work with the handicapped. Their activities led to the establishment of many programs, such as the Pennsylvania Association for the Blind, the Industrial League (for the sale of items made by handicapped people), and the Bertha F. Rauh Nursery School for the Deaf. Many of the projects initiated by the Section were taken over by other agencies, became independent, or disappeared when the need for them was gone.
  - Rules for the Guidance of Personal Service Workers, 1901 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Report to Immigrant Aid Committee, 1906 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Reports and correspondence, Penal Work Committee, 1920-1921 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Statement, summer camp for working girls, 1921 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Reports, Department of Social Services, 1920s-1930s (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Reports, employment, 1933-1935 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Report, Girls Bureau, 1937 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Handicapped, Work for the blind, 1932-1975 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Handicapped, Work for deaf and hard of hearing, 1930s-1962 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Handicapped, Industrial League, 1928-1956 (Box 18, Folder 10-13)
  - Handicapped, Cerebral Palsy program, 1949-1964 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Handicapped, Committee for the handicapped, 1951-195(?) (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - Handicapped, Bertha F. Rauh Nursery School for the Deaf, 1952-1958 (Box 18, Folder 16-19)
  - Handicapped, Reports, history, and correspondence, Recreation Bureau, 1932-1935 (Box 18, Folder Unknown container 6010 for instance of Handicapped, Reports, history, and correspondence, Recreation Bureau)
  - Minutes, Grants, Scholarships, and loans to Jewish students, and Student Aid Committee, 1949-1965 (Box 19, Folder 1-2)
  - Treasurer reports, 1949-1965 (Box 19, Folder 3-5)
  - Correspondence, contributions, and Senatorial scholarships, 1934-1971 (Box 19, Folder 6-8)
  - Relationship with United Vocational Employment Services/Vocational Rehabilitation Center, 1952-1969 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Student Aid Committee members and recipients, 1929-1959 (some undated) (Box 19, Folder 10-14)
  - Student Aid recipients, A-K (Box 20)
  - Student Aid recipients, L-Z (Box 21)
  - Council House for working girls, 1923-1932 (Box 22, Folder 1-5)
  - Foreign Born Files
    - Minutes, Committee of Service to Foreign Born, 1939-1946 (Box 22, Folder 6-9)
    - Reports, 1932-1961 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Committee members and correspondence, 1940-1953 (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - Relief campaign for Jews in Germany, 1933 (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - German Jewish Children's Aid Committee, 1934-1936 (Box 22, Folder 13-17)
    - Rescue Children, Inc., 1946 (Box 22, Folder 18)
    - Emergency supplies for new Americans, 1949-1950 (Box 22, Folder 19)
    - Citizen's Committee on Displaced Persons, 1946-1950 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Visiting Committee on Service to Foreign Born, 1948-1954 (Box 23, Folder 2-4)
    - Immigration and nationality laws, 1952-1953 (Box 23, Folder 5-7)
    - Committee on Immigration and Naturalization of Allegheny County, 1955-1958 (Box 23, Folder 8-9)
    - Joint Committee on service to new immigrants, 1955-1958 (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - United Service for new Americans, 1949-1954 (Box 23, Folder 11-15)
    - American Service Institute, 1947-1958 (Box 23, Folder 16-19)
    - Friendship Club, 1950-1964 (Box 23, Folder 20)
    - Russian Resettlement Party, 1957 (Box 23, Folder 21)
    - Country Club luncheon and Invisible Port and Dock luncheon, 1940-1941 (Box 23, Folder 22-23)
- Community and Overseas Services, 1927-1980; IX.
  Series IX contains materials of the Pittsburgh Section's work with community and overseas projects. From the mid-1940s on the Pittsburgh Section's philanthropic activities changed in accordance with changing conditions. While continuing its services to the foreign born, the section developed new programs of outreach for the aged, hospitalized veterans, mentally ill, and children in need. Files concerning legislation for the aged includes correspondence from U.S. Senator Joseph Clark, State Senator Michael O'Pake, Louis H. Rosenthal Memorial Institute "Our Senior Citizens-The Legislative Road to Dignity," and a tape recording from the institute located in Box 55. Additional correspondence includes letters from local clergymen, agency executives, U.S. Representatives Elmer J. Holland and William S. Moorhead, U.S. Senators Hugh Scott and Joseph S. Clark, and County Commissioner William D. McClelland.
  The Pittsburgh Section also participated in NCJW programs overseas, including Ship-A-Box, which sent educational and play materials for kindergartens abroad. They also created fellowships for students abroad and initiated the Hebrew University High School project. Locally, the Council innovated the Share-A-Toy program with hospitals in Israel.
  In the Services for the Aged subseries there is information on a number of activities and projects, including Anathan House, Central Bureau on the Care of the Aged (CBCA), and various senior citizen programs. The bulk of the records in the subseries are from 1941-1980, and contain reports, publications, planning and architect records, history and surveys. The subseries on Work with Children and Youth has information on pre-school health programs, the Headstart program, children's enrichment programs, and Delinquent Children and Adoptive and Foster Care Procedures.
  - Services for the Aged, 1.
    - Community Service Bureau Department, 1952-1980 (Box 24, Folder 1-3)
    - Central Bureau on the Care of the Aged (CBCA), 1941-1953 (Box 24, Folder 4-6)
    - Reports, Social Committee for the Aged in the Community, 1949-1951 (some undated) (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Plans for cooperative programs for the aged, 1949-1951 (some undated) (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - City-wide aged recreational project, 1952-1960 (Box 24, Folder 9-10)
    - Camping for older people, 1951-1953 (some undated) (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - Statistical surveys of aged, 1941-1961 (intermittent) (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - Legislation for the aged, reports, position papers, and correspondence, 1961-1975 (Box 24, Folder 13-16)
    - County and State committees on aging, 1953-1975 (Box 24, Folder 17)
    - White House conferences on aging, 1961-1962 (Box 24, Folder 18)
    - Have a Heart for the Aged (legislation for medical care insurance) (Box 24, Folder 19)
    - Friendly Visitors and Meals on Wheels, 1958-1975 (Box 24, Folder 20)
    - Transportation for elderly (with Pioneer Women), 1973-1975 (Box 24, Folder 21)
    - Senior Citizens Service Corps, 1966-1976 (intermittent) (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Retired Senior Volunteer Program (RSVP), 1974 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Services for elderly, East End, 1974 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Senior Citizens Month, 1966-1969 (intermittent) (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Problems of aged, programs, and publications, 1944-1972 (intermittent) (Box 25, Folder 5-7)
    - Council Lounge for the elderly, 1949-1963 (Box 25, Folder 8-22)
    - Anathan House, 1962-1976 (Box 26, Folder 1-16a)
  - Work with Children and Youth Files, 2.
    - Child Study Committee report, Campaign for a Child Welfare Service reports and correspondence, 1927-1928; 1961-1963 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Delinquent children reports, correspondence, and publications, 1954-1975 (Box 27, Folder 2-4)
    - Squirrel Hill Youth Council, 1947 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Allegheny County Conference on Family Life, 1949-1952 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Essay contest for college seniors, 1952-1953 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Infant and Pre-School Health Section, Department of Public Health, Arsenal Public Health Center, and Volunteer Project, 1951-1958 (Box 27, Folder 8-12)
    - White House conferences on children and youth, 1960 and 1970 (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Children's Cultural Enrichment Program reports, correspondence, and newspaper clippings, 1963-1966 (Box 27, Folder 14-15)
    - Headstart Day Care Committee reports, proposals, volunteer information, and correspondence, 1967-1976 (Box 27, Folder 16-20)
    - Adoptive and foster care procedures, Allegheny County, 1969-1970 (Box 27, Folder 21-22)
    - Tutorial Project, jointly with Bethesda United Presbyterian Church and Community Center of Homewood, UJF, JCC, Brashear Association, 1968-1975 (Box 28a, Folder 1-2)
    - Community Committee on School Dropout and Youth Employment and Committee on Employment Impact, 1960-1968 (Box 28a, Folder 3-7)
    - Lifestyle Program publications and Learning Disabilities Project, 1961-1975 (Box 28b, Folder 8-10)
    - Creative Dramatics/Mental Health Teacher Assistant Program, 1970-1976 (Box 28b, Folder 11-14)
    - Emotionally ill children, with Poale Zedeck School and Technoma Workshop, 1961-196(?) (Box 28b, Folder 15)
    - Public Schools and Citizen's Commission, correspondence, 1952-1976 (Box 28b, Folder 16-20)
    - Third Annual Louis H. Rosenthal Memorial Institute, "Bills, Budgets and Bonuses for our Schools", March 1, 1963 (Box 28b, Folder 21)
    - Project Forward (Box 28b, Folder 22)
    - Subject files, abortion, adoption, child abuse, and international child of the year (Box 28b, Folder 23-26)
- Health and Welfare Services, 1946-1973; X.
  Series X consists of materials of the Pittsburgh Section's activities with health and welfare services. The Pittsburgh Section is noted for introducing the visiting nurse to Pittsburgh. In addition, the section has often worked in association with other organizations in providing volunteers for health and welfare programs. The subseries on Health Services contains a history, correspondence, minutes, reports, members from the Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County, and other organization materials for the period 1946 to 1973. In the subseries Mental Health Programs there is information on the history, minutes, reports, financial records, program services, and information regarding Council House social rehabilitation for mental patients (under community auspices from 1967) for the period 1957 to 1973.
  - Health Services, 1.
    - Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County, 1946-1973 (Box 29, Folder 1-10)
    - Citizens Association for Health and Welfare, 1949-1958 (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, Inc. and Polio Vaccination Program, 1951-1957 (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - USO volunteers, 1956-1957 (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - Veterans Administration Voluntary Service (VAVS), 1950-1957 (Box 29, Folder 14-24)
  - Mental Health Programs, 2.
    - Mental Hygiene Committee/Mental Health Committee, 195(?)-1962 (intermittent) (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Mental Health Conference, correspondence and agendas, 1956-1957 (Box 30, Folder 2-3)
    - Mental Health Public Hearings, Pennsylvania Department of Welfare, 1956 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Academy of Religion and Mental Health, 1969 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Citizens Liaison Committee on mental health, 1971 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Mental Health Publications by NCJW, Pennsylvania and Department, HEW, U.S. (Box 30, Folder 7-8)
    - Council House social rehabilitation for mental patients, 1957-1973 (Box 30, Folder 9-21)
    - Diagnostic and counseling services for the mentally handicapped (Box 30, Folder 22)
- Political Action, 1929-1979; XI.
  Series XI contains records on the Pittsburgh Section's political activities. The Pittsburgh Section was involved in political action for many decades. Some activities were short lived, such as Liberation Day and Pennsylvania Week, but other activities have gone on for years, such as the section's involvement in the Human Relations Commission between 1952 and 1973. The Council involves itself in political action on the local, state, national and international levels, with particular interest in Jewish affairs.
  This series contains information on the Department of Public Affairs Files (previously the Department of Education, the Bureau of Education, the Bureau of Education and Social Action, and the National and International Affairs), Fair Employment Practice Commission (FEPC), Fair Housing Practices Committee (FHPC), Club Women of Western Pennsylvania, Human Relations Commission, and civil rights. Of importance to the civil rights subseries is the information regarding Marjorie H. Watson and her work with the Allegheny County Council on Civil Rights.
  - Department of Public Affairs, 1.
    - Reports and correspondence, 1927-1979 (Box 31, Folder 1-5)
    - Committee on Classes and Discussion Groups and Committee on State Affairs (Box 31, Folder 6-7)
    - Legislative Club (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - The Banner, 1952-1954 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - Washington Institute on Public Affairs, 1958-1978 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Second Louis H. Rosenthal Legislative Institute, "Tools for Understanding the News", March 27, 1962 (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - Political questionnaires, Congressional candidates, state candidates, and Senator Clark, 1950-1968 (Box 31, Folder 12-15)
    - Pennsylvania State Tax Reform, 1970 (Box 31, Folder 16a)
    - Clean Air Committee, 1969 (Box 31, Folder 16b)
    - Anti-Ballistic Missile, 1969 (Box 31, Folder 16c)
    - Call for Action, 1970 (Box 31, Folder 16d)
    - Education Committee, 1969-1977 (Box 31, Folder 16e)
    - Bicentennial convocation on religious liberty, 1975-1977 (Box 31, Folder 16f)
    - Welfare rights, 1969 (Box 31, Folder 16g)
    - American Foundation for Political Education, 1958 (Box 31, Folder 17)
    - Association of Community Councils of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, 1947 (Box 31, Folder 18)
    - Civic Club of Allegheny County, 1954-1959 (Box 31, Folder 19)
    - Civil Defense reports, correspondence, and publications, 1950-1957 (Box 31, Folder 20-22)
  - Civil Rights, 2.
    - Allegheny County Council on Civil Rights, 1948-1958, 1968 (Box 32, Folder 1-9)
    - Fair Employment Practice Commission (FEPC), 1948-1956 (Box 32, Folder 10-15)
    - Fair Housing Practices Committee (FHPC), 1953-1974 (Box 32, Folder 16-22)
    - Pennsylvania Equal Rights Council, 1958 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous material on civil rights, 1963-1967 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Congress of Clubs and Club Women of Western Pennsylvania, 1947-1958 (Box 33, Folder 3-9)
  - Federation of Women's Clubs, 3.
    - Allegheny County Federation of Women's Clubs, 1948-1958 (Box 33, Folder 10-17)
    - Pennsylvania Federation of Women's Clubs, 1947-1958 (Box 33, Folder 18-19)
    - Household Employment Committee, 1965-1967 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Human Needs Coalition, 1973-1974 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Human Relations Commission, 4.
    - Human Relations Commission, 1957-1973 (Box 34, Folder 3-4)
    - Human Service Board of Allegheny County, 1974 (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - League of Women Voters, 1956-1969 (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - Liberation Day (contains proclamation signed by Mayor David Lawrence), May 5, 1950 (Box 34, Folder 7)
    - National Achievement clubs, 1950-1956 (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), 1949-1974 (intermittent) (Box 34, Folder 9)
    - National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1948-1958 (Box 34, Folder 10-11)
    - National Conference of Social Work, 1938-1947 (Box 34, Folder 12-13)
    - Pennsylvania Tax Reform study group, 1970 (Box 34, Folder 14)
    - Women's Advisory Committee, Pennsylvania Week, 1947-1951 (Box 34, Folder 15-16)
    - Pittsburgh Coalition on National Priorities and Military Policy, 1969-1970 (Box 34, Folder 17)
    - Pittsburgh Council on Intercultural Education, 1949-1957 (Box 34, Folder 18-19)
    - Pittsburgh Council for International Visitors report, June 11, 1962 (Box 34, Folder 20)
    - Police Community Relations Project, 1972-1974 (Box 35, Folder 1-2)
    - Public Assistance study group, 1968-1969 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Urban League, 1953-1966 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - WQED, 1954-1957 (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Women in Community Service Corporation (WICS), 1964-1971 (Box 35, Folder 6-12)
    - Women in the Urban Crisis of Western Pennsylvania (see also FHPC files), 1967-1975 (Box 35, Folder 13-17)